树 屋
字 幕 组
M 小 队
2010年2月24日 奥兰多海洋世界
Orange County Fire Rescue.
橘郡消防救援
6600 Sea Harbor Drive.
海港大道6600
SeaWorld Stadium.
海洋世界场馆
树屋字幕组-M小队 荣誉出品
Okay.
好的
We actually have a trainer in the water
我们有一个驯兽师
with one of our whales--
和一条鲸鱼一起进到了水中
the whale that they're not supposed to be in the water with.
那条鲸鱼是不应该和驯兽师一起进到水中的
Okay. We'll get somebody en route.
好的 我们会找巡逻人员过来处理
翻译 小奇 踢歪 静子
Okay, through gate #3 to Shamu Stadium.
好的 从3号门进到虎鲸游泳池
Gate 3.
3号门
Orange County Sheriff's Office.
橘郡警长办公室
We need SO to respond
我们需要安全观察员
for a dead person at SeaWorld.
对海洋世界的一个死者作出回应
特效\压制\校对 小新
Uh, a whale has eaten one of the trainers.
呃 一条鲸鱼把一个驯兽师吃了
A whale ate one of the trainers?
一条鲸鱼把一个驯兽师吃了？
That's correct.
是的
黑 鲸
Do you believe?
你相信吗?
My parents first brought me to a SeaWorld park
很小的时候 我父母第一次带我到
when I was very young.
海洋世界公园
From that point forward, I was hooked.
从前面那一点看 我震惊了
It meant everything to me because
这对我来说意味着一切
约翰·哈格罗夫
前海洋世界驯兽师
I'd never wanted anything more.
因为我从没想要过更多
I remember being probably in first or second grade
我记得大概在一二年级时
watching National Geographic specials
看国家地理频道的特辑
or Mutual of Omaha specials
或者奥马哈互动特辑
and seeing whales and seeing dolphins and as a little kid
看到鲸鱼和海豚 作为一个小孩子
just being really incredibly inspired by it.
我备受鼓舞 真是令人难以置信
萨曼莎·伯格
前海洋世界驯兽师
I never went to SeaWorld.
我从来没有去过海洋世界
I grew up in New York, so I went to the Bronx Zoo.
我在纽约长大 所以我去过布朗克斯动物园
Grew up on a lake with horses. We'd swim the horses.
在湖边和马群一起长大 我们会让马游泳
I grew up around the ocean.
我在海边长大
I came from the middle of the country in flatland Kansas.
我来自美国中部的堪萨斯平原
I'm from Virginia.
我来自弗吉尼亚州
Traveled down, did the theme park thing
在奥兰多从事主题公园的工作
马克·西门斯
前海洋世界驯兽师
in Orlando when I was 17
那时我才17岁
and saw the night show at Shamu Stadium.
我在虎鲸馆看到了晚间表演
Very emotional, you know, popular music.
表演非常感人 音乐很受欢迎
And I was just-- I was very driven to want to do that.
我备受驱动 很想从事那个工作
Then I saw what the trainers did...
当时我看到驯兽师所做的一切...
and I said, "That's what I want to do."
我说 这就是我想要做的
One of the trainers there, he goes,
有一个驯兽师在那说
"What are you doing out there? You should be a trainer."
你在那外面干什么工作? 你应该做驯兽师
I go, "I don't know how to train animals.
我说 不知道如何训练动物
I've never trained animals in my life."
我生平从来没有训练过动物
How do you prepare yourself for an encounter
当你遇到一条8000磅重的虎鲸
with an 8,000-pound Orcinus orca?
你如何武装自己?
I always thought you needed, like, a master's degree
我一直以为需要海洋生物学硕士学位
in marine biology to be a trainer.
才能成为驯兽师
It takes years of study and experience
这需要多年的研究和经验
to meet the strict requirements necessary
以满足严格的要求
to interact in the water with Shamu.
在水中与虎鲸互动
Come to find out, it really is more about
最后发现 这不仅仅是你的个性
your personality and how good you can swim.
和你游泳技术有多好的问题
I went and tried out, got the job right away.
我去参加选拔 马上就得到了这份工作
I'm like, "Yeah!" So excited, you know.
我兴奋得耶的一声大叫起来
I was so, so excited.
我非常 非常兴奋
I really wanted to be there. I really wanted to do the job.
我真的很想到那里 我真的很想做这个工作
I couldn't wait to get in the water with the animals.
我迫不及待地与动物进到水中
I really was proud of being a SeaWorld trainer.
作为一个海洋世界驯兽师 我真的感到很骄傲
You know, I thought this was the most amazing job.
我认为这是最了不起的工作
I showed up there on my first day, not really knowing what to expect.
我出现在那里的第一天 真的不知道该期待什么
卡萝·雷
前海洋世界驯兽师
I was told to put on a wetsuit and get in the water.
有人叫我穿上潜水衣并进到水中
Hi, Mom!
嗨 妈妈!
Oh, I was scared out of my wits.
噢 我被吓得魂飞魄散
First of all, I put my wetsuit on backwards
首先 我把潜水衣穿反了
because I was raised on a farm in Virginia.
因为我是在弗吉尼亚州的一个农场上被抚养长大的
- Hi, Dad! - My first thought
-嗨 爸爸!   -我的第一个念头
and memory of that time was that dolphins are a lot bigger...
和记忆是 当你进到水中
...heh, than they look
与它们相邻时
when you get in the water next to them.
它们远比看上去要大得多
Well, I watched the Sea Lion & Otter Show,
我看过海狮和水獭的表演
迪恩·戈默索尔
前海洋世界驯兽师
and this guy, Mike Morocco,
这家伙 迈克·摩洛哥
he comes out during the show with a dress on as Dorky,
在表演期间他穿着一条连衣裙
the alter ego of Dorothy--
像多萝西的另一面一样傻乎乎地走出来
in a dress with a sea lion, the Coward Sea Lion, right?
他穿着连衣裙和一头懦弱海狮在一起 对吗?
And he's walking along with this little basket,
他正拿着他的小篮子一路走
and I go, "I will never, ever do that."
然后我说"我永远都不会那样做"
You know? Two months later...
你知道吗? 两个月之后...
Hi, I'm Dorky!
我就对大家说 嗨 我是傻猪!
Walking out onstage with a sea lion.
然后我就和一头海狮走到舞台上
I was overwhelmed and I was so excited.
我不知所措 同时我又如此兴奋
I mean, just seeing a killer whale...
我是说 看到鲸鱼杀手
is breathtaking.
这是使人透不过气来的事情
I was just in awe.
我只是觉得敬畏
It's shocking to see how large they are
看到它们如此巨大 如此美丽
约翰·杰特
前海洋世界驯兽师
and how beautiful they are.
真是令人震惊
Being in the presence of the killer whales
在虎鲸面前
was just inspiring and amazing,
是多么鼓舞人心和令人惊异
and I remember seeing them for the first time,
我记得第一次看到他们
just not being able to believe how huge they were.
简直不能相信它们是如此巨大
You're there because you want to train killer whales and that's your goal.
你在那里是因为你要训练虎鲸 这是你的目标
Yay!
啊!
I didn't know it was going to happen,
我不知道它会发生
so I wasn't expecting it.
所以我并不指望它会发生
And one day they say, "Okay, Sam, you're ready to go."
一天他们说 "好的山姆 你已经准备好了"
Come on, you got it.
来吧 你能行
"You're going to stand on the whale.
"你要站在鲸鱼身上
You're going to dive off the whale.
你要在鲸鱼身上跳水
The whale's going to swim under you and pick you up again.
然后鲸鱼游到你下面 并再把你接住
And then you're going to do a perimeter ride around the pool."
然后你要乘着鲸鱼在水池周边周旋一圈"
Good!
好!
Keep moving. Ride him to the slide-out.
继续前进 骑着它然后滑出来
They just told me to go do it and I did it.
他们叫我去做 而且我做到了
Wow, I did-- I just rode a killer whale.
哇 我做到了 我骑了虎鲸
Yay, girly!
啊 乖乖女!
When you look into their eyes, you know somebody is home.
当你看着他们的眼睛 你就知道有人在家
Somebody's looking back.
有人在往回看
You form a very personal relationship with your animal.
你和动物形成了一个非常个人化的关系
There's something absolutely amazing
和动物一起工作
about working with an animal.
绝对是令人惊异的
You are a team.
你们是一个团队
You build a relationship together.
你们共同建立起合作关系
You both understand the goal and you help each other.
你们都明白目标是什么 并互相帮助
I've been with this whale since I was 18 years old
自从18岁起 我就和这条鲸鱼一起工作了
and I've seen her have all four of her babies.
我见过她诞下所有四个婴儿
We've grown up together. Huh?
我们一起长大 是吗?
That's the joy I got out of it.
这就是我从中得到的快乐
It's a relationship like I've never had.
这是我从没有过一种关系
Bro, I have to know-- are you nervous?
兄弟 我得知道 你紧张吗?
I'm scared.
我很害怕
- Oh, no. - Nice hair, Jeff.
-噢 不   -好漂亮的头发 杰夫
Did you see anything?
你有没有看到什么东西?
Projection for the future of Jeff Ventre.
预测未来的杰夫·文特雷
杰弗瑞·文特雷
前海洋世界驯兽师
Jeff Ventre is going to go over there, he's going to shine.
杰夫·文特雷将要到那边去 他将要大放异彩
- You're going to notice... - Dawn.
-你会注意到...   -道恩
- Oh, that's Dawn. - Wow.
-噢 那是道恩   -哇
He's going to be my supervisor one day.
某天他会成为我的上司
There you go.
就这样
I knew Dawn when she was new.
我认识道恩时她还是新人
She was a great person to work with
她是一个很棒的合作伙伴
and she obviously blossomed into one of SeaWorld's best trainers.
她显然发展成为海洋世界最好的驯兽师之一
This is Dawn Brancheau.
这是道恩·布兰切
Dawn is the senior trainer here at Shamu Stadium.
道恩是虎鲸馆的高级驯兽师
I guess you could say I kind of knew Dawn in a past life.
我想你可以说我多少有点知道道恩的过去
It's a tough job, isn't it?
这是一个艰难的工作 是吗?
Yeah, we really do go through a lot of physical exertion.
是的 我们确实经历了很多强体力活动
You can see in the show we do a lot of deepwater work,
你可以在表演中看到我们做了很多深水下的工作
breath holds, very high-energy behaviors with animals.
屏住呼吸 这是非常高能量的动物行为
Obviously they're giving out a lot of energy too,
很显然 他们也消耗了大量的精力
but we're working together and having a lot of fun as well.
但我们一起共事 也有很多的乐趣
She's beautiful, she's blonde, she's athletic, she's friendly.
她很漂亮 金发 体格健壮 又友好
You know, everybody loves Dawn.
每个人都喜欢道恩
And I mean this so sincerely,
我很真诚地说
watching you perform yesterday-- you're amazing.
昨天看了你的表演 你真是太棒了
- Thank you. - You really are.
-谢谢你  -你确实是太棒了
She captured what it means to be a SeaWorld trainer.
她捕捉到作为海洋世界驯兽师的意义所在
She had so much experience that it made me realize
她如此多的经历 让我认识到
what happened to her really could have happened to anyone.
发生在她身上的事同样很可能发生在任何人身上
2010年2月24日
橘郡治安部门 - #10-16715 报案
This is Detective Revere
我是橘郡警长办公室
with the Orange County Sheriff's Office.
的里维尔探长
里维尔探长
Today's date is February 24, 2010.
今天的日期是2010年2月24日
接见
海洋世界护理人员
托马斯·托宾
The time is 4:16.
时间是4:16
In the room with me right now is a Thomas George Tobin.
现在和我在房间的是一个托马斯·乔治·托宾
- Is that correct? - Correct.
-对吗?  -对
你当时注意到水中有任何的血迹
或者类似的东西了吗?
呃 准确来说
她已经 呃 抬上来整理好了
没有看到血
好的
所以 我们所知道的更多的就是
她的心脏已经停止跳动了
他们曾经把她拉离虎鲸
虎鲸是怎么放开她的...
他没有
他没有放开...呃..
手臂?
手臂
他吞掉了
他吞掉了?
- So the arm is nowhere... - Right.
-那么手臂已经找不到了...   -对
职业安全和健康管理局
控告
佛罗里达海洋世界有限责任公司
OSHA, on behalf of the federal government,
职业安全与健康管理局(OSHA) 联邦政府的代表
is basically suggesting that swimming with orcas
他们的基本意思是 与虎鲸一起游泳本身是危险的
is inherently dangerous and that you can't completely predict
当你进入到水中或进入他们的环境中时
the outcome when you enter the water or enter their environment.
你不能完全预测事情的结果
That's the crux of the OSHA case.
这是职业安全与健康管理局案子的症结所在
Stay out of proximity with the animals and you won't get killed.
不要亲近动物 这样你就不会被杀
戴夫·达弗斯
OSHA专家鉴定人
鲸鱼研究学家
It will have a ripple effect through the whole industry.
它会对整个行业产生连锁反应
This was national headline news.
这是国家头条新闻
SeaWorld's whale performances
海洋世界的鲸鱼表演
may never be the same.
可能从来不相同的
Right now the theme park is arguing in court
现在主题公园在法庭上争论
to keep whale trainers in the water,
以保持鲸鱼的水中培训
something OSHA says is extremely dangerous.
职业安全与健康管理局说是极其危险的东西
These are wild animals, and they are unpredictable
这些都是野生动物 他们是不可预测的
because we don't speak whale.
因为我们不说鲸鱼语言
We don't speak whale, we don't speak tiger,
我们不说鲸鱼的语言 不说老虎的语言
we don't speak monkey.
不说猴子的语言
And tempers flared between the two sides today
今天 职业安全与健康管理局的代理律师认为
when OSHA's attorney suggested that SeaWorld only made changes
海洋世界在驯兽师道恩布兰切死后才对水中训练作出改进
after trainer Dawn Brancheau's death outraged the public.
激怒了公众 双方之间的怒气突然爆发
OSHA doesn't want the trainers going back in the water
职业安全与健康管理局不想驯兽师
without a physical barrier between them and the whales.
在他们和鲸鱼之间没有物理屏障的情况下回到水中训练
Being in close proximity to these top predators is too dangerous.
亲近这些顶级掠食者真是太危险了
They won't then be getting in the water
也就是说 他们不能再做
riding on the whales, things like that.
在水中骑在鲸鱼身上之类的事了
If you were in a bathtub for 25 years, don't you think you'd get
如果你在浴缸里生活25年 难道你觉得
a little irritated, aggravated, maybe a little psychotic?
你一点儿也不会动怒 恼火 或许有点儿发疯吗?
The situation with Dawn Brancheau-- it didn't just happen.
道恩布兰切的情况不仅仅是突然发生这么简单
It's not a singular event.
这是不是个案
You have to go back over 20 years to understand this.
你必须追溯到20多年前才能明白这一点
三十九年前...
1970年普吉特海湾 华盛顿州
It was a really exciting thing to do
这是一个非常令人兴奋的事情
约翰·克罗
潜水者
and so everybody wanted to do it.
所以每个人都想做
What were they telling you you were going to do?
他们叫你干什么?
Mm, capture orcas.
嗯 捕捉虎鲸
Whoo-hoo!
哇哈!
They had aircraft,
他们有飞机
they had spotters, they had speedboats,
测位仪和快艇
霍华德·加雷特
虎鲸研究者
they had bombs they were throwing in the water.
他们有扔在水中的炸弹
They were lighting their bombs with acetylene torches in their boats
他们在船上用乙炔火炬把炸弹点燃
and throwing them as fast as they could
然后尽可能快地扔出去
to herd the whales into coves.
把鲸鱼赶到海湾
Whoo!
哇!
But the orcas had been caught before
但虎鲸以前被抓捕过
and they knew what was going on
他们知道怎么回事
and they knew their young ones would be taken from them.
他们知道幼小的鲸鱼会被抓捕
So the adults without young went east into a cul-de-sac
所以成年鲸鱼抛弃幼鲸向东游进死胡同
and the boats followed them, thinking they were all going that way,
船只紧跟其后 认为它们正向那边游去
while the mothers with babies went north.
同时母鲸和幼鲸往南游去
But the capture teams had aircraft.
但捕鲸队有飞机啊
And they have to come up for air eventually.
而且它们最终还是必须浮上来呼吸空气
And when they did, the capture teams alerted the boats
当它们浮上来时 捕鲸队就向船只发出警报
and said, "Oh, no, they're going north-- the ones with babies."
说 噢 不 它们带着幼鲸往南游去
So the boats-- the speedboats caught them there
快艇就在那追上它们
and herded them in.
把它们赶进去
And then they had fishing boats with seine nets
然后他们有围网渔船
that they would stretch across so none could leave
把围网横跨撒去 无一漏网
and then they could just pick out the young ones.
然后他们就可以把幼鲸挑出来
We were only after the little ones.
我们只追捕幼鲸
And a little one is, you know, a big animal still.
然而对于我们来说 幼鲸仍然是很大的动物
But I was told because of shipping costs
但有人告诉我 他们只要幼鲸
that's why they only take the little ones.
其原因是运输成本过高
They had the young ones that they wanted in the corrals,
他们已经有想要的幼鲸在围栏里了
so they dropped the seine nets.
所以们把围网拿掉
And all the others could have left, but they stayed.
其它所有鲸鱼都本可离去 但它们不愿离去
We're there, trying to get the young orca into the stretcher,
我们就在那 试图把幼虎鲸放到担架上
and the whole famn damily is out here,
整个家庭就在外面
25 yards away maybe,
也许是25码的距离
in a big line...
形成一条大大的阵线
...and they're communicating back and forth.
他们在来回地交流
Well...
嗯
you understand then what you're doing, you know.
然后 你就明白你在做什么
I-- I lost it.
我不知所措
I mean, I just started crying.
我是说 我哭了起来
I didn't stop working,
我并没有停止工作
but I...
但我...
you know, I just couldn't handle it.
我无法控制
Just like kidnapping a little kid away from their mother.
就像从他们的母亲身边把一个小孩绑走
Everybody's watching. What can you do?
每个人都在看 你能怎么样?
It's the worst thing I can think of, you know?
这是我所能想到的最糟糕的事情 你知道吗?
I can't think of anything worse than that.
我想不出比这更糟糕的事情
Now, and this really sounds bad,
现在 这听起来真的很糟糕
but when the whole hunt was over,
但整个追捕结束时
there were three dead whales in the net.
网里有三条死鲸
And...
还有...
so they had Peter and Brian and I...
所以他们让彼得 布赖恩和我
cut the whales open, fill them with rocks,
把死鲸剖开 往它们肚子里装石头
put anchors on their tail, and sink them.
把锚挂在他们的尾巴上 让它们沉入海底
Well...
嗯...
you know...
你知道的...
really, I didn't even think about it
说真的  在那时那刻
being illegal at that point.
我甚至没有想到这是非法的
I thought it was a PR thing.
我以为这是公共关系的事情
They were finally ejected from the State of Washington
1976年 他们终于被法院勒令
by a court order in 1976.
逐出华盛顿州
It was SeaWorld by name that was told,
所被告知的名字是海洋世界
"Do not come back to Washington to capture whales."
"不要回到华盛顿去捕捉鲸鱼"
Without missing a beat, they went from Washington to Iceland
不加思索地 他们就从华盛顿到冰岛
and began capturing there.
并在那里开始捕鲸
I've been part of a revolution and two change of presidents
我曾经历过中 南美洲的一次变革
in Central and South America...
和两次总统换届
and seen some things that's hard to believe,
见过一些难以置信的东西
but this is the worst thing that I've ever done--
但是我做过的最糟糕的事情
is hunt that whale.
就是捕鲸
1983年一只雄性虎鲸被捕获于北大西洋
两岁 已经达到了11.5英尺长
它被人们取名为提里库姆
Sealand has been a part of Victoria for over 20 years.
海洋之地公园已经成为维多利亚的一部分超过20年了
We specialize in the care and display of killer whales.
我们专门从事对虎鲸的照料和展示
By the time I started, when he was four,
它才4岁 我就开始训练它了
埃里克·沃尔特斯
海洋之地前驯兽师
he was up to 16 feet long and weighed 4,000 pounds.
他长16英尺 重达4000磅
Tilikum, up again.
提里库姆 再上来一次
Thank you.
谢谢
I had actually seen Tilikum quite a number of times.
我曾多次见过提里库姆
肯·鲍尔科姆
鲸鱼研究中心主任
He was right across the street here in Victoria.
他就在维多利亚的街对面
Now, this show can get a little bit soggy at times.
现在 这个表演有时可能有点湿漉漉的
All Sealand was was a net hanging in a marina
整个海洋之地就是挂在码头上的
with a float around it.
一个四周布满浮板的网
Tilikum was the one we really loved to work with.
提里库姆是我们非常喜欢与之合作的一条鲸鱼
He was very well behaved and he was always eager to please.
他表现得非常出色 总是热心于取悦观众
When he was first introduced, everything just went fine and dandy,
他首次被介绍的时候 一切都十全十美
but the previous head trainer
但前总教练使用了
史蒂夫·赫克斯特
海洋之地前主管
used techniques that involved punishment.
涉及处罚的表演技术
He would team a trained orca up with Tilikum who was untrained.
他会把训练有素的虎鲸和未经训练的提里库姆组成一队
He would send them both off to do the same behavior.
他会将他们俩罚下场去做同样的行为
If Tilikum didn't do it, then both animals were punished.
如果提里库姆做不到 两者都要受罚
Deprived of food to keep them hungry,
剥夺食物 让他们捱饿
this caused a lot of frustration with the larger animal,
对这群巨型动物带来了很大的挫折
the established animal,
已经被训练过的虎鲸
and would in turn get frustrated with Tilikum
会反过来会对提里库姆感到沮丧
and would rake him with his teeth.
然后就会用牙齿耙它
There would be times during certain seasons
某些特定季节期间
that Tilikum would be covered head to toe with rakes.
提里库姆总会由头到尾布满齿耙
Rakes are teeth on teeth and raking the skin.
齿耙就是咬着牙齿往皮肤上耙
And from head to toe you could see blood
从头到尾 你可以看到鲜血
and you could see scratches, and he would just be raked up.
你可以看到划痕 它会被耙伤的
Both females would gang up on him.
两条雌鲸会联合起来对付他
Tilikum was the one we trusted.
我们相信提里库姆
We never were concerned about Tilikum.
我们从不担心提里库姆
The issue was really that we stored these whales at night
真正的问题是 为安全起见
in what we call a module, which was 20 feet across
我们晚上把鲸鱼安置在我们所说的
and probably 30 feet deep as a safety precaution
大概20英尺宽30英尺深的分离舱里
because we were worried about people cutting the net and letting them go.
因为我们担心有人会把网割烂以让它们逃走
And the lights were all turned out, so there was really no stimulation.
所有灯都关掉 所以真的没有刺激性
They're just in this dark, metal 20x30-foot pool
他们就在漆黑的 20X30英尺的金属水池里
for two-thirds of their life.
度过三分之二的生命
When we first started,
我们刚开始训练时
they were quite small and quite young.
它们还很幼小
So they fit in there quite nicely,
因此他们在那里适应得相当不错
but they were immobile for the most part.
但在大多数情况下 他们是一动不动的
It didn't feel good. It just didn't.
我就是觉得这样不好
And it was just wrong.
这样是不对的
We started having difficulty getting them all
老实说 我们开始有把他们
克里斯托弗·波特
海洋之地前训练员
into this one small steel box, to be honest.
都弄到这个小铁箱里的困难
That's what it was. It was a floating steel box.
这就是事实的真相 那是一个漂浮的铁箱
That's where food deprivation would come in.
这就是食物匮乏发挥作用的地方
We would hold back food,
我们会把食物往回拉
and they would know if they went in the module
它们就会知道如果进了那个分离舱
that they would get their food.
它们就会得到食物
So if they're hungry enough, they're going to go in there.
所以如果他们饿够了的话 他们就会进去那里
And during the winter that would be
冬季时期会从晚上
from 5:00 at night till 7:00 in the morning.
5:00直到上午7:00
抱歉我们已关门
鲸鱼正在休息中请明日再来参观
十点开门
When you let them out, you'd see these new tooth rakes
当你让他们出去时 你会看到这些新的齿耙
and sometimes you'd see blood.
有时你会看到鲜血
Closing that door on him
关上门
and knowing that he's locked in there for the whole night is like...
就知道它一整晚被锁在那里就像
it's a stab, it's a "whoa."
"哇"心里一阵刺痛
If that is true, it's not only inhumane,
如果这是真的 我会告诉他们
and I'll tell them so...
这不仅不人道
but it probably led to what I think is a psychosis that...
但我认为它可能导致一种精神病
he was on a hair trigger.
一触即发
He'd kill.
它会杀人
An employee is dead after an encounter...
一名雇员在一次事故后死亡...
...at a Canadian park called Sealand of the Pacific.
...在加拿大一个叫太平洋海洋之地的公园里
The victim, Keltie Byrne, was a championship swimmer
受害者凯尔蒂·伯恩是游泳冠军
and a part-time worker at Sealand.
是海洋之地兼职工人
As seen in this home video, rescuers used a huge net to try...
在这个录像里看到 救援人员用一个巨大的网试图...
...rescue workers' efforts were hindered by the agitated whales.
...救援人员的努力受到激动鲸鱼的阻碍
I'd like to make the Pan Pacific team this summer,
我想在今年夏天参加泛太平洋队
but my more immediate goal is just to swim fast at nationals.
我更迫切的目标是想在国际赛事中游的更快
1991年2月20日 - 维多利亚
科琳·克威尔和纳丁·卡伦参观了太平洋海洋之地公园
It was sort of a cloudy, gray day
那是一个有点多云的阴天
and we were looking for something to do,
我们正在找事做
so we thought, "Why not go to Sealand?"
所以我们想"为什么不去海洋之地?"
It was kind of like this dingy pool with these whales and--
这有点像是装着鲸鱼的昏暗水池
it just felt a little bit like an amusement park
只是感觉有点像一个游乐园
that was kind of on its last legs and everything was a bit gray.
大概是在行程的最后一站 所以什么都有点灰色的感觉
Yeah. It was like a swimming pool.
是的 那好像是一个游泳池
科琳·克威尔
纳丁·卡伦
- Yeah, yeah. - You know,
-是的 是的   -你知道的
three whales in a swimming pool.
有三条鲸鱼在游泳池里
Yeah.
是的
And they would come up and touch the ball and there was--
他们会上来碰球
I think there was some tail splashing and there was some--
那有鱼尾戏水
- Some jumping. - The fish. And--
-也有跳水  -还有鱼
They hold the fish and the whales jump up.
他们把鱼拿在手上鲸鱼就会跳起来
I remember saying, "Oh, what a fun job.
我记得我在说"噢 多么有趣有工作"
You know, she's so lucky."
她是如此幸运
And then I saw her walking with her rubber boots
然后我看见她穿着胶靴在走
and she tripped and her foot just dipped into the edge of the pool
然后她绊了一下 她的脚浸入池边
and she lost her balance and fell in.
失衡掉进水里
And then she was pushing her way up to get out of the pool
然后她起身离开游泳池
and the whale zoomed over, grabbed her boot,
但鲸鱼飞快地游过来 咬住了她的靴子
and pulled her back in.
把她拖了回去
At first, I didn't think it was that serious
起初 我想没有那么严重
because you see the trainer in the pool with the whale
因为你看到驯兽师和鲸鱼一起在泳池里
and you think, "Oh, well, the whales are used to that."
你就想"噢 鲸鱼已习惯这样子"
And then all of a sudden, it started getting--
然后突然之间 情况开始变严重了
there was more swimming, more activity, more thrashing,
她使劲游 做了很多动作 多次鞭打鲸鱼
and she was starting to get panicked.
她开始恐慌
And then as it progressed, you started to realize,
然后因为事情发展 你开始认识到
"Whoa, something's not right here."
"哇 有点不对劲儿"
She started to scream and she started looking around
她开始尖叫起来 她开始四处张望
and her eyes were, like, bigger and bigger
她的眼睛越来越大
and realizing that, "I really am in trouble here."
并意识到"我真的遇上麻烦了"
And then they would pull her under.
然后它们会把她拉到水下
And then they would come up and then when she--
然后会游上来
they came up, she'd be, "Help me, help me."
当它们游上来 她会大喊 救命 救命
And then they'd take her down again.
然后它们又把她拖下去
And she would be submerged for several seconds
她会被淹没几秒钟到大概一分钟
up to, I don't know, maybe a minute.
到大概一分钟 我也不知道
You're not keeping track.
并没有跟踪计时
So it was harder and harder for her to get the air in
所以她呼吸越来越困难
because she was screaming.
因为她在尖叫
And my sister remembers her saying, "I don't want to die."
我妹妹记得她说"我不想死"
Well, condolences to Keltie's family.
我们向凯尔蒂家人表示哀悼
Yeah.
是的
That we couldn't help her
们帮不了她
was pretty wretched.
真遗憾
Sealand closed. Well, it's probably a good thing.
海洋之地关闭了 这可能是一件好事
戴夫·达弗斯
OSHA鉴定专家 鲸鱼研究者
I mean, it was a little pond.
我的意思是 这只是一个小池塘
And I think the owner,
不管什么原因
you know, made the right decision for whatever reasons.
我都觉得老板做出了正确的决定
I don't believe he's a bad guy, a bad man.
我不相信他是一个坏人
I think he was shocked by the whole affair, too.
我想他也对整个事件感到震惊
The blush was gone from the business
公司荣誉扫地
and he decided that that was it.
他决定就这样算了
We should shut down.
我们应该停业
No one ever contacted us. There was an inquest.
没有人和我们联系 只有审讯调查
No one ever asked us to say what happened.
也没人问发生了什么事
- Yeah. - You know, we just left.
-是的   -我们离开了
There was no big lawsuits afterwards and there was no memorial.
之后没有大型诉讼也没有追悼会
And the only thing remaining of Keltie Byrne is--
凯尔蒂·拜恩唯一剩下的是
is what's left in the folks' minds who recall the case.
残留在人们脑海中对案件的回忆
So in the newspaper articles,
所以报纸上的报导说
the cause of death was that she drowned accidentally,
她的死因是意外溺毙
but she was pulled under by the whale.
但她是被鲸鱼拉到水里的
Well, there's a bit of smoke and mirrors going on.
事件有点像雾里看花
I mean, one of the fundamental facts is is that none of the witnesses
我是说 一个基本的事实是没有一个证人
were clear about which whale pulled Keltie in.
明确看到是哪条鲸鱼把凯尔蒂拉下水的
Yes. Yeah, it was the large whale.
是的 是那条巨大的鲸鱼
Tilikum, the male, is the one that went after her.
追逐她的那条雄鲸是提里库姆
And the other two just kind of circled around.
其他两条只是在她周围盘旋
But he was definitely the instigator.
但他绝对是始作俑者
And we knew it was that whale because he had the flopped-over fin.
我们知道是那条鲸鱼是因为他有上下跳动的鱼鳍
Like, it was very easy to tell.
很容易分辨
Sealand of the Pacific closed its doors and was looking, I guess,
我想 太平洋海洋之地关了门
to make a buck on the way out
并一直在寻找赚钱的出路
杰弗里·文特雷
海洋世界前驯兽师
and these whales are worth millions of dollars.
而且这些鲸鱼价值数百万美元
When SeaWorld heard that Tilikum was available
当海洋世界听说
萨曼莎·伯格
海洋世界前驯兽师
after this accident at Sealand of the Pacific,
提里库姆在太平洋海洋之地这起事故后尚可使用
they really wanted Tilikum because they needed a breeder.
他们真的很想要提里库姆是因为他们需要一条繁育鲸
So I don't even think that anybody even was questioning,
我甚至认为没有人会质疑
like, is this a good idea?
比如问 这是不是一个好主意?
My understanding of the situation was that Tilikum and the others
我了解的情况是 提里库姆和其它鲸鱼
would not be used in shows.
将不会再用于表演
They would not be performance animals.
他们不会是拿来做表演的动物
Our understanding of their behavior
我们对他们的行为理解是
was that it was such a highly stimulating event for them
这是一个高度刺激着
that they were likely to repeat it.
他们乐此不彼地重复的事情
Sealand was-- we were all young and bit of sea cowboys
我们都年轻 有点像海上牛仔
and we weren't so technical and scientific as SeaWorld,
我们没有海洋世界那么有科学性和技术性
so we all had this vision that they knew more than us
所以我们都有这个展望 他们比我们懂得更多
and they were better than us and Tilikum would have
比我们更优秀 提里库姆会有更大的水池
a bigger pool and he'd have a better life
会有更好的生活
and he would have better care and he'd have better food
会得到更好的照料 会有更好的食物
and it'd be a great life for him.
对它来说 这将会是精彩的生活
So it was like, "Okay, Tilly.
所以就像我说的"好的 提里
You're going to Disneyland. Lucky you."
你将要去迪斯尼乐园 你真幸运"
The orcas' intelligence
虎鲸的智力
《虎鲸》(纪录片) 迈克尔·安德森导演 派拉蒙出品
may be even superior to man's.
甚至可能比人类还要高
As parents, they are exemplary, better than many human beings.
作为父母 他们是模范 比许多人类做得更好
And like human beings, they have a profound instinct for vengeance.
像人类一样 他们有强烈的复仇天性
Dino De Laurentiis presents...
劳伦蒂斯呈献...
..."Orca."
...虎鲸
If you go back only 35 years, we knew nothing.
如果你回到35年前 我们一无所知
In fact, less than nothing.
事实上 不及虚无
What the public had was superstition and fear.
公众所拥有的是迷信和恐惧
A fight to the death...
这是地球上两个
between the two most dangerous animals on Earth.
最危险的动物之间的死亡斗争
What in hell are you?!
你到底是什么?!
These were the vicious killer whales
这些是狠毒的虎鲸
that, you know, had 48 sharp teeth
有48个锋利的牙齿
that would rip you to shreds if they got a chance.
如果有机会的话 它们会将撕裂你撕成碎片
What we learned is that they're amazingly friendly
但我们了解到的是 他们友好得令人惊讶
and understanding and intuitively want to be your companion.
善解人意并直观地想成为你的同伴
Are you recording this?
你在录像吗?
And to this day there is no record
迄今为止 没有任何虎鲸
of an orca doing any harm to any human in the wild.
在野外对人类造成任何伤害的记录
They live in these big families.
它们住在这些大家庭里
And they have life spans very similar to human life spans.
它们的寿命和人类的寿命很相似
The females can live to about 100, maybe more,
雌性鲸鱼大约能活到100岁 甚至更长
males to about 50 or 60.
雄性黑鲸能活50到60岁
But the adult offspring never leave their mother's side.
但成年子女是不会离开它们母亲半步的
Each community has a completely different set of behaviors.
每个群体之间的行为迥异
Each has a complete repertoire of vocalizations
每个群体都有一个系统的发声系统
with no overlap.
不会重复
You could call them languages.
你可以将之称为是语言
The scientific community is reluctant to say
虽然科学界不愿承认
any other animal but humans uses languages,
除了人类的任何动物能使用语言
but there's every indication that they use languages.
但是种种迹象表明它们使用语言
The orca brain just screams out
鲸鱼的大脑大声喊出它们拥有
罗莉·马里诺
神经系统科学家
intelligence, awareness.
智力 意识
We took this tremendous brain
我们把这个巨大的大脑
and we put it in a magnetic resonance imaging scanner.
放进了核磁共振成像扫描仪内
What we found was just astounding.
发现了令人震惊的事实
They've got a part of the brain that humans don't have.
它们拥有我们人类没有的一部分大脑
A part of their brain has extended out
它们的一部分大脑
right adjacent to their limbic system.
直接连接到它们的边缘系统
The system processes emotions.
这个系统处理情绪
The safest inference would be these are animals
保险推断 这些动物
that have highly elaborated emotional lives.
有着复杂的情感生活
It's becoming clear that dolphins and whales
我们已经明确 海豚和鲸鱼
have a sense of self, a sense of social bonding
拥有自我感知和社会联系
that they've taken to another level--
这就上升到了另一个层面--
much stronger, much more complex
一个更强烈 更复杂的层面
than in other mammals, including humans.
比起任何哺乳动物 甚至是人类
We look at mass strandings,
我们可以看到在搁浅的时候
the fact that they stand by each other.
它们都是一起搁浅
Everything about them is social-- everything.
它们做的一切都有关社交--任何事
It's been suggested that their whole sense of self
有人提出 它们的自我感知
is distributed among the individuals in their group.
分散在它们群里的个人之中
There are five of them.
有五只鲸鱼
These orca are going to attack this seal on--
这些虎鲸将要攻击这只海豹--
they've been breaking the ice off and swimming around him.
它们正在打破坚冰 在他附近游泳
Oh, here they come, two of them. Lookit, underneath there.
噢 它们来了 有两只 看 在下面
You can see them underneath.
你可以看到它们在水下
They made a big wave. Look at that, a big wave.
它们掀起了大波浪 快看 大波浪
-Oh, yeah.   - Whoa.
-噢 是啊   -哇
-Oh, God.    -Oh, God. No, no, no.
-噢 天哪   -噢 天哪 不 不 不
Oh! Oh, I can't stand it.
噢! 噢 我受不了了
If you can't watch the bullfight, you'd better leave.
如果你连斗牛都看不了 你最好现在就离开
Oh, yeah, here they go. Look at this-- three of them.
噢 是啊 它们来了 看着--有三只鲸鱼
Look at this. Look at this.
快看 快看
Oh, God. Oh, no!
噢 上帝 噢 不!
-Oh, God!    -It's all over.
-噢 天哪!   -结束了
Nope, not quite.
不 还没结束
Yeah, it's all over.
是的 都结束了
It's all over.
结束了
The First Nations people and the old fishermen on the coast,
海岸上的原住民和老渔夫
they call them "blackfish."
他们叫它们"黑鲸"
They're an animal that possesses great spiritual power
它们是拥有强大精神力量的动物
and they're not to be meddled with.
它们不会瞎闹
I've spent a lot of time around killer whales
我花了很多时间观察虎鲸
and they're always in charge.
它们一直都在我的看管之下
I never get out of the boat, I never mess with them.
我从来没有离开过船 我从来没有干扰过它们
The speed and the power is quite amazing.
它们的速度和力量让人震惊
Rules are the same as the pool hall--
这里的规则和台球房的规则是一样的--
keep one foot on the floor at all times.
你始终得确保一只脚在地上
Even after seeing them thousands of times...
尽管已经见过它们上千次...
you see them and you still--
在看到它们的时候你仍然--
you know, wake up.
你懂的 瞬间清醒
He arrived, I think, in 1992.
他来到这里 我记得 是在1992年
I was at Whale and Dolphin Stadium when he arrived.
我当时正好在鲸鱼和海豚场
And he's twice as large as the next animal in the facility.
他的体型是设施里的其他动物的两倍
Yay!
耶！
The guy is right at about 12,000 pounds.
这个家伙大概有12,000磅
That's incredible. He looks fantastic.
难以置信 他看起来太不可思议了
When Tilikum arrived at SeaWorld,
当提里库姆来到海洋世界
he was attacked viciously, repeatedly by Katina and others.
他反复被卡蒂娜和其他鲸鱼恶意欺负
In the wild, it's a very matriarchal society.
在野外 这是一个典型的母系社会
Male whales are kept at the perimeter.
雄性鲸鱼以体型分类
In captivity,
在收容设施中
the animals are squeezed into very close proximity.
这些动物被硬塞进非常狭小的空间
Tilikum-- the poor guy is so large,
提里库姆--这个倒霉的家伙太大了
he couldn't get away because he just is not as mobile
他不能逃跑因为他不像
relative to the smaller and more agile females.
其他小的鲸鱼或是灵敏的雌性鲸鱼
And where was he going to run? There's no place to run.
他能跑到哪里去呢? 根本没有地方可去
I think he spent a lot of time in isolation.
我觉得他大部分时间都是被孤立的
SeaWorld claims that, "Oh, no, he's always in with the other--
海底世界宣称:"噢 不 他总是和其他鲸鱼在一起--
with the females," but from what I saw,
和雌性鲸鱼"但就我看来
he was mostly put with the females for breeding purposes
把他和雌性鲸鱼放在一起只是为了繁殖
and he didn't spend a lot of time, you know, with the other whales.
他也不会花费很多时间 你知道的 和其他鲸鱼在一起
It's for his own protection that he gets beat up.
这是他防止被暴打的自我保护
约翰·杰特
海洋世界前驯兽师
And so by segregating him,
所以把他孤立起来
it provides a physical barrier so the females can't kick his butt.
为他提供了一个物理屏障 所以雌性鲸鱼欺负不到它
Tilikum is pretty much kept in the back,
提里库姆大部分时间都被安置在后面
and then brought out at the very end as, like, the big splash.
然后在最后关头才被带出来 像是 用来制作大水花
He was always happy to see you in the morning.
他在早上看到你的时候总是很开心
-Hi!   -There we go.
-嗨!  -我们走
-You're the boy.   -Look at his chompers.
-就是你呀   -看看他的大嘴巴
Maybe because he was alone, maybe because he was hungry,
可能是因为他很孤独 可能是因为他很饿
maybe because he just liked you--
也可能是因为他喜欢你--
who knows what was going on in his head.
谁知道他在想什么呢
You want to whistle?
你想吹口哨?
--All right, so he can talk to us.
--好啊 所以它能跟我们对话
-Yes.    -You don't say.
-是的   -你没说过
He's precious. Yes?
他很可贵 是吗?
That was really loud. Terrific.
还真是够响啊 太棒了
-Come on, big boy.    -Show the pecs.
-来吧 大家伙   -秀秀你的胸大肌
He seemed to like to work. He seemed to be interested.
他似乎喜欢工作 他似乎很感兴趣
He seemed to want to learn new things.
他似乎想去学新的东西
He seemed to be enjoying working with the trainers.
他似乎很享受和训练者一起工作
He, for me, was a joy.
他 对我来说 是一份欢乐
He really responded to me and I--
他真的会回应我而且我--
you know, every day I went to work, I was happy to see Tilly.
你知道 每天我去上班 我都很高兴能看到Tilly
-Boop!    -That's cute.
-啵!   -好可爱
You're being too cute.
你怎么那么可爱
I never got the impression of him while I was there
我在这里的时候对他从来没有过这样的印象
that, oh, my God, he's the scary whale.
就是 噢 我的天哪 他是个可怕的鲸鱼
Not at all.
根本不是
Maybe some of it's just our naiveté or whatever,
可能有些是因为我们的天真或是什么
you know, because we weren't given
你懂的 因为我们没有给予
the full details of Keltie's situation.
Keltie的处境的足够细节
Turn around. Smile, buddy.
转过来 笑一下 伙计
-Cheese.   -Yay!
-茄子   -耶!
I was under the impression that Tilikum had nothing to do
提里库姆给我的印象就是他肯定
with her death specifically, that it was the female whales
和她的死亡没有任何关系 肯定是那些雌性鲸鱼
who were responsible for her death.
需要对她的死付出代价
What I found really odd at first was the way they were acting
一开始我发现奇怪的地方是他们的反应
around this whale and what they had told us
对于这条鲸鱼的 但他们所告诉我的
seemed to me to be two different things.
在我看来根本是两码事
The first day he arrived, I remember
他来这里的第一天 我记得
one of the senior trainers at SeaWorld, she--
一个海洋世界的高级培训师 她--
Tilikum was in a pool and she was walking over a gate,
提里库姆在池子里 而她从门口走进来
and she had her wetsuit unzipped and it was tied around her waist.
她没有拉好她的潜水服 就挂在她的腰上
And she was making cooing noises and going,
她轻声说道
"Hey, Tilikum, what a cute little whale."
"嘿 提里库姆 真是头可爱的小鲸鱼呀"
And she was, like, just kind of play-talking at him,
然后她就像是 在和他打闹交流
and one of the supervisors said, "Get her out of there!"
其中一个主管就说来:"把她带出去！"
And just screamed at her, like, "Get her away from there,"
就直接对她喊 像是:"快把她带出去"
like they were so worried that something was going to happen.
就像是他们很担心马上会发生些什么
And I remember thinking, "Why are you guys making
我记得我在想"为什么你们这些家伙
such a big deal out of this when he didn't actually kill her?"
这么紧张? 他又没有要杀了她"
Well, clearly management thought there was some reason
好吧 显然管理部门认为有一些原因
to exercise caution around him.
需要小心谨慎地对待他
You know, clearly they knew more than they were telling us.
你知道的 显然他们不会把他们知道的都说出来
Ladies and gentlemen, the next two behaviors you're going to be seeing,
女士们先生们 接下来的你将看到的表演
you can only see right here at SeaWorld.
你只能在海洋世界欣赏到
Jeff was out in the audience filming one of the Shamu shows.
Jeff坐在观众席里拍摄虎鲸的表演
It was a perfect show.
那是一个完美的秀
All of the hot dog sequences,
安排的滴水不漏
the water works sequences went off great.
供水装置也很完美
I was really excited just to be capturing this
我很激动能记录下这场演出
because it was kind of turning out to be a great show.
因为这是一场无与伦比的演出
A show that's kind of complete--
是一场完整的演出--
it doesn't-- it probably only happens a few times a week.
它不--它一个星期可能只发生几次
At the very end of the show, Liz was working Tilikum
在演出最后结束的时候 利兹和提里库姆一起工作
and apparently Tilikum lunged out of the water at her.
显然提里库姆向她泼水花
And I had captured Tilikum coming out of the water
我记录下了提里库姆冲出水面的瞬间
kind of turning sideways and appeared to me
就像是侧过身子 在我看来
to try to grab Liz.
就像是想抓住利兹
And at that moment,
在那个时候
the tape became unusable.
录像带无法使用了
I was just kind of basically instructed to get rid of the tape.
我就像是有点受到暗示的 想摆脱掉那盘录像带
Wanting to kind of preserve the tape, I actually used the editing equipment
因为想要保存下录像带 事实上我用了些编辑设备
and snipped out that little half-second or second
剪辑了那半秒还是一秒的画面
when he did that and stitched it back together
在他做那个动作的时候 然后再剪辑在一起
so it just kind of looked like a glitch in the tape.
所以带子里看上去就是有点小故障
And I'm like, "Look at this." And it was like, "No.
然后我就像是 "看这个" 然后就像是 "不
This is no longer usable."
这个不能用了
You know, and so we had to destroy the tape.
所以我们只得毁了胶带
职业安全与健康管理局
交叉询问
佛罗里达海洋世界有限责任公司
海洋世界驯兽师主管
凯莉·克拉克
提里库姆没有任何预兆让我觉得它会冲出水面
OSHA律师
约翰·布兰克
但是你知道它是有能力冲出水面的吧?
我也知道你有强奸别人的能力
我不得不告诉你所有男人都有成为强奸犯的潜质
法官
肯·威尔士
关于这个论点我们搁置再议
It's pretty outrageous that SeaWorld would claim
所以这的确有点离谱 海洋世界宣称
there was no expecting Tilikum to come out of the water
提里库姆没有要冲出水面的迹象
because they had witnessed him coming out of the water,
因为他们曾经亲眼目睹他冲出水面
and it's written into his profile.
而且这一点有写进他的简历
He lunges at trainers.
他冲向训练者
When we visit SeaWorld, we tend to take advantage of the fact
在我们游览海洋世界的时候
that Shamu has been provided with a safe and comfortable habitat.
我们给虎鲸提供了一个安全舒适的居住环境
And everything trained is an extension
所有的训练都是可调整的
of the killer whale's natural behavior.
根据虎鲸的本能行为
I spewed out the party line during shows.
我在演出中不断欺骗观众
I'm totally mortified now.
我现在很羞愧
There was like-- something like, "Look at Namu.
那就像是--像是 "看纳姆
卡萝·雷
海洋世界前驯兽师
Namu's not doing that because she has to."
纳姆做这一切不是因为她必须得做"
Namu is doing this because she really wants to.
纳姆做这一切是因为她想这么做
Oh, my gosh.
噢 我的天呐
Like, some of the things I'm embarrassed by,
就像是 这令我感到羞愧
so embarrassed by.
太羞愧了
At the time, I think I could have convinced myself
在那时 我还以为我能说服我自己
that the relationships that we had were built on something
我们之间建立起来的关系
stronger than the fact that I'm giving them fish.
要比单纯的我喂食它这个层面要强韧的多
You know, I like to think that...
你知道 我喜欢这么想...
but I don't know that that's the truth.
但我不知道就是这样
I had been there a while and I had seen a few other things along the way
我在那里工作过一段时间 一路上我也看到了许多其他事情
that made me question why I was there
让我质疑 为什么我会在这里
and what we were doing with these animals.
我们在和这些动物做什么
1990年海洋世界广告
On November 4, 1988,
在1988年11月4日
a killer whale at SeaWorld
海底世界的一头虎鲸
gave the performance of a lifetime.
上演了千载难逢的演出
Don't miss this small miracle.
不要错过这个小奇迹
Come see our new Baby Shamu.
过来看看我们的新虎鲸宝宝
I know it was naive of me,
我知道是我天真
but I thought that...
但我认为...
it was our responsibility to do as much as we could
努力做我们所能做的是我们的职责
to keep their family units together
为了保证它们的家庭团结
since we knew that in the wild that's what happens.
既然我们知道他们在野外是这样的
♪ Yes, sir, that's our baby... ♪
是的 先生 这就是我们的宝宝...
Kalina was the first Baby Shamu.
卡利娜是第一只虎鲸宝宝
Baby Shamu-- SeaWorld's newest star...
虎鲸宝宝-- 海洋世界的新星
She had become quite disruptive and challenging her mom a little bit
她变得有破坏性的 开始挑战她的母亲
and disrupting some shows and that kind of thing.
开始扰乱一些演出 做这之类的事情
♪ She's got the whole place jumpin' ♪
她能穿梭在整个地方
♪ Shamu, she's that baby whale. ♪
虎鲸 她就是那头鲸鱼宝宝
It was decided by the higher-ups that she would be moved
上级决定她将会被移到
to another park when she was just four, four and a half years old.
另一个公园在她只有四岁的时候 四岁半的时候
And that was news to us as trainers that were working with her.
这对我们和与她共事的训练者来说很是震惊
To me, it had never crossed my mind
对我来说 我根本没有想过
that they might be moving the baby from her mom.
他们会把鲸鱼宝宝从它母亲身边带走
The supervisors basically was kind of mocking me,
主管有点像是嘲弄我的
like, "Oh, you're saying, 'Poor Kalina,"'
就像是"噢 你是说 可怜卡利娜"
you know, "'what's she going to do without her mommy?"'
"她离开了她母亲之后怎么办?"
And, you know-- and that of course just shut me up.
还有 然后我就哑口无言了
So, the night of the move, we had to deploy the nets
所以 在搬运的那天晚上 我们得布置好网
to separate them and get Kalina, the baby, into the med pool.
用来分开她们 然后把卡利娜 鲸鱼宝宝 搬运到地中海池
And Katina was generally a quiet whale.
卡提娜通常情况下是一头安静的鲸鱼
She was not an overly vocal whale.
她不是那种会过度大叫的鲸鱼
After, Kalina was removed from the scene
在这之后 卡利娜就被移走了
and put on the truck and taken to the airport,
被装上了卡车 然后带去了机场
and Katina, her mom, was left in the pool.
然后卡提娜 她的妈妈 就被留在了池子里
She stayed in the corner of the pool,
她呆在了池子的角落里
like, literally just shaking and screaming,
就像是 简直就像是在颤抖和叫喊
screeching, crying.
尖叫 哭泣
Like, I had never seen her
像是 我从来没见过她
do anything like that.
这幅样子
And the other females in the pool,
池子里其他的雌性鲸鱼
maybe once or twice during the night
在晚上有一次到两次
they'd come out and check on her.
她们出来找她
And she'd screech and cry and they would just run back.
然后她就开始尖叫哭泣 她们就直接回去了
There was nothing that you could call that,
你根本毫无办法
watching it, besides grief.
除了看着她 同情她
Those are not your whales.
那些不是你的鲸鱼
You know, you love them and you'll think,
你知道的 你爱它们 你会觉得
"I'm the one that touches them, feeds them, keeps them alive,
"我是那个抚摸它们 喂养它们 哺育它们
gives them the care that they need."
给予它们需要的照顾的人"
They're not your whales.
它们不是你的鲸鱼
They own them.
他们才拥有它们
Kasatka and Takara were very close.
卡萨特卡和塔卡拉非常亲近
Kasatka was the mother, Takara's the calf.
卡萨特卡是妈妈 塔卡拉是她的孩子
Takara was special to me.
塔卡拉对我来说很特别
They were inseparable.
她们是不可分割的
When they separated Kasatka and Takara,
当他们把卡卡萨特卡和塔卡拉分开的时候
it was to take Takara to Florida.
塔卡拉要去弗罗里达
Once Takara had already been stretchered out of the pool,
一次塔卡拉已经被弄出了池子
put on the truck, driven to the airport...
被搬进卡车 在开往机场的路上...
Kasatka continued to make vocals
卡萨特卡一直在发出声音
that had never been heard before.
这是以前从来没有过得
They brought in
他们请了
the senior research scientists to analyze the vocals.
资深研究员来分析这些声音
They were long-range vocals.
它们是远程的声音
She was trying something
她在用一些
that no one had even heard before looking for Takara.
从来没有人听过的声音寻找塔卡拉
That's heartbreaking.
这实在是令人心碎的
How can anyone
怎么可能会有人
look at that and think that that is morally acceptable?
看到了这一切 还会认为这是符合道德情理的?
It's not.
不是
It is not okay.
绝对不是
Stand by, Dean.
准备好 迪恩
Let's go live to SeaWorld
让我们去看看海洋世界的现场
where Dean Gomersall is joining us for a sneak peek.
迪恩·戈默索尔将会带我们先睹为快
Hi, Dean. Tell us about the new show.
嗨 迪恩 跟我们说说最新的演出
Good afternoon, Richard.
下午好 理查德
The new show is the Whale and Dolphin Discovery.
新的演出是发现鲸鱼和海豚
What it does is it shows the relationship we have
它展示的是我们人类
between all our animals here at the Whale...
和动物之间的关系 和鲸鱼...
There's so many things that were told to us
我们被告知了许多事情
that they tell us-- they tell you so many times
他们告诉我们-- 告诉我们许许多多次
迪恩·戈默索尔
海洋世界前驯兽师
that you just-- you start believing it.
然后你就-- 你就开始相信它了
So all the animals here get along very well.
这里所有的动物都相处得非常好
It's just like training your dog, really.
就像是在训练你自家的小狗一样 真的
I was blind, you know. I was a kid.
我当时很盲目 你懂的 我还是个孩子
I didn't know what I was doing, really.
我不知道我在干什么 真的
-Nice.    -Good job.
-太棒了   -好样的
You did a real good job.
真是好样的
Ladies and gentlemen, this is David from Maryland.
女士们先生们 这位是来自马里兰的大卫
Go ahead and wave at everyone, David.
继续前进 和大家挥挥手大卫
I just really bought into what they told us.
我就真的被他们所告我的所迷惑了
You know, I learned to say what they told us to the audience.
你知道的 我开始对观众说他们安排的话
Hello out there.
大家好
Children are some of Shamu's biggest fans.
孩子们是虎鲸最大的粉丝
We can do just about anything we want.
我们能做一切我们想做的事情
I thought I knew everything about killer whales when I worked there,
当时我在那边工作的时候 我以为我知道关于虎鲸的一切
you know, and everything about these animals.
你知道 关于那些动物的一切
I really know nothing about killer whales.
其实我对它们根本一无所知
I know a lot about being an animal trainer
我知道怎么去做一名动物训练师
or a killer whale trainer, but I don't know anything
或是一名虎鲸训练师 但剩下的我什么都不知道
about these animals' natural history or their behavior.
关于那些动物的自然史以及本能
I really in some ways believed a lot of what I was learning from them,
在某种程度上我真的相信了很多他们所告诉我的话
because why would they lie?
因为 他们为什么要说谎?
Because the whales in their pools die young,
因为他们养殖的鲸鱼去世地很早
they like to say that all orcas die at 25 or 30 years.
他们就说鲸鱼的平均寿命在25岁到30岁
-25 to 35 years.   -25 to 35 years.
-25到30岁   -25到30岁
They're documented in the wild living to be about...
结果表明 在野外鲸鱼的平均寿命大约是...
35, mid-30s.
35岁 30中旬
They tend to live a lot longer in this environment
他们在这样的环境中能活得更长
because they have all the veterinary care.
因为他们有兽医的照顾
And of course that's false.
当然这是假的
We knew by 1980, after half a dozen years of the research,
我们在1980年得知 在研究了六年之后
that they live equivalent to human life spans.
鲸鱼的寿命几乎等同于人类的寿命
And every other potentially embarrassing fact is twisted
但所有其他的潜在的令人为难的事实都被扭曲了
and turned and denied one way or another.
然后被拒绝承认
So, in the wild, they live...
所以 在野外 他们的寿命...
-Less.   -Less.
-更短   -更短
Like the floppy dorsal fins.
就像是松软的背鳍
25% of whales have a fin that turns over like that
25%的鲸鱼的鳍会这样翻转过来
as they get older.
随着他们年龄的增长
Dorsal collapse happens in less than 1% of wild killer whales.
在野外 背鳍衰竭在虎鲸中发生的概率少于1%
We know this.
这我们也知道
All the captive males 100% have collapsed dorsal fins.
所有被捕获的雄性鲸鱼100%都有背鳍衰竭现象
And they say that they're a family, that the whales are in their family.
他们就说它们是一家人 鲸鱼和它们的家人生活在一起
They have their pods.
它们有它们的亲属
But that's just an artificial assemblage of their collection,
但这只是一个人造的家庭
however management decides they should mix them
不管怎样 管理人员决定把他们混淆
and whichever ones happen to be born
不管是哪个碰巧出生
or bought and brought in.
或是带来带去的
That's not a family, you know. Come on.
这根本不是家庭 拜托
You've got animals from different cultural subsets
我们有着来自不同文化子集的动物
that have been brought in from various parks.
他们都来自不同的公园
These are different nations.
他们是不同的族类
These aren't just two different killer whales.
他们不单纯是两头不同的虎鲸
These animals, they've got different genes,
这些动物 他们有不同的基因
they use different languages.
他们使用不同的语言
Well, what could happen as a result of them being
好吧 这些有可能发生是
thrown in with other whales that they haven't grown up with,
他们被安排幼年没有接触过的鲸鱼一起生活
that are not part of their culture
根本不是他们文化中的一部分
is there's hyperaggression...
这是他们亢奋的竞争...
...a lot of violence, a lot of killing in captivity
...许许多多暴力 在被俘虏中有许许多多杀戮
that you don't ever see in the wild.
这是你根本在野外见不到的
For the health and safety of the animals,
为了动物的安全和健康
please do not put your hands in the water.
请不要把你的手放在水里
It was always sort of this backdrop,
总是在这种背景下
this underpinning of tension between animals.
这种动物中紧张的基础
Whale-on-whale aggression was just part of your-- the daily existence.
鲸鱼和鲸鱼之间的侵犯是一部分-- 这是日常存在的
We ask that you use the stairs and aisleways as you exit.
离开时请使用楼梯走道
Please do not step on the seats.
请不要踩在椅子上
These areas may become wet
那些区域有可能变湿
and therefore slippery to some footwear.
导致滑倒
Thank you.
谢谢
♪ Blue wonder... ♪
蓝色奇迹...
In the wild, when there's tension,
在野外 当它们不安的时候
they've got thousands of square miles
它们有上千平方公里
to exit the scene and they can get away.
来逃离远离这一切
You don't have that in captivity.
但在收容设施中就不是这样了
Could you imagine being in a small concrete enclosure for your life
你能想象一辈子被关在一个狭窄的混凝土围场里
when you're used to swimming 100 miles a day?
而你以前习惯一天游100英里?
♪ Free-feeling... ♪
自由的感觉...
Sometimes this aggression became very severe
有时候这种侵犯变得很严重
and, in fact, whales have died in captivity because of this aggression.
事实上 因为这种侵犯 鲸鱼会在收容设施中死亡
I think it was 1988.
我想是在1988年
Kandu, trying to assert her dominance over Corky,
堪度想要维护她对科奇的统治
rammed Corky.
冲向科奇
It fractured her jaw, which cut an artery in her head
她的下巴裂了 割到了她头上的动脉
and then she bled out.
然后她就血流不止
Now that's got to be a hard way to go down.
现在肯定很难平静下来
I saw that there was just a lot of things that weren't right.
我看到有许多事情都不正确
And there was a lot of it-- misinformation--
有许多--错误的信息--
and something was amiss.
还有一些 有差错的
And, you know, I sort of compartmentalized that part of it
还有 你知道 我区分了一部分
and did the best that I could with the knowledge that I had
我用我的知识做了所能做的一切
to take care of the animals that were there.
去照顾那里的动物
You know, I think all the trainers there have the same thing in their heart.
你知道 我想所有的训练师也是这么想的
They're trying to make a difference in the lives of the animals.
他们尝试在它们的生命中创造不同
You think that, "if I leave, who's going to take care of Tilikum?"
你会这么想 "如果我走了 谁来照顾提里库姆?"
That's why I stayed. Because I felt sorry for Tilikum.
这就是为什么我留下了 因为我为提里库姆感到抱歉
I mean, if you want to get down to the nuts and bolts of it,
我是说 如果尝试考虑具体细节
I stayed because I felt sorry for Tilikum.
我留下来了 因为我为提里库姆感到抱歉
And I couldn't bring myself to stop coming
我不能阻止我自己看望
and trying to take care of him.
以及照顾他
Gosh, do I love coming out here every day
天呐 我热爱每天来这里
and having the audience just love what we're doing with the animals.
同时通过演出让观众也爱上它们
How do I make this animal as beautiful as they are
我该怎么做才能让它展现美丽
and have people walk away loving this animal?
然后让人们爱上这只动物?
And they're touched and they're moved
让他们感动触动
and I feel like I made a difference to them.
我觉得我和他们是不同的
I left in January of 2010,
我在2010年1月的时候离开了
a month before Dawn passed away.
在道恩去世前的一个月
金姆·阿什道恩
海洋世界前驯兽师
She was like a safety guru.
她就像是一个安全专家
I mean, she was always double-checking,
我是说 她总是仔细检查
making sure that everyone was doing the right thing.
来确保每个人做的事情都是正确的
So I remember she would record every show that she did
我记得她会记录下她的每一场演出
and she would watch it and critique herself.
然后她会看这些演出 然后批评她自己
She was constantly trying to be better.
她不断地要求更好
When I found out it was Dawn,
当我发现那是道恩的时候
I was shocked.
我震惊了
That could have been me. I could have been the spotter.
那有可能是我 我有可能是监视人
What if I was there and I could have saved her?
如果当时我在那里 我有没有可能救起她?
You know, all these things go through your mind.
所有的这一切在我脑海里萦绕
John Sillick is the guy who, in 1987,
约翰·希力克他在1987年
was crushed between two whales at SeaWorld of San Diego.
在圣地亚哥的海洋世界被两头鲸鱼压死
Now, even though I'd been working at SeaWorld for six months,
现在 尽管我在海洋世界已经工作了6个月
I had no idea that that had even happened.
但我根本不知道有这么一回事
I never even heard that story.
我从来都没有听说过这样的故事
And the SeaWorld party line was that, well, that was-- it was a trainer error.
海洋世界觉得就像是 好吧 像是-- 那只不过是训练失败而已
It was John's fault. You know, John's fault.
那是约翰的失误 约翰的失误
He was supposed to get off that whale.
他本应该从那头鲸鱼上下来的
And for years, I believed that and I told people that.
许多年来 我深信不疑 我也是这么告诉别人的
I actually started at SeaWorld, like, five days after that event occurred
事实上 我开始在海洋世界工作 是 在那件事发生的5天之后
and we didn't-- we weren't told much about it
但是我们-- 我们没有被告知太多
other than it was trainer error.
除了那是个训练失误
And, you know, especially when you're new into the program,
你知道的 特别当你是这个项目的新人时
you don't really question a whole lot.
你不能问太多问题
Well, you know, years later, when you actually look at the footage,
好吧 要知道 几年后 当你真的看着那个镜头
you go, "You know what? He didn't do anything wrong."
你就知道 "你知道吗? 他根本什么也没做错"
That whale just landed on him, you know.
鲸鱼就这么猛烈撞击他 你懂的
That whale just went to the wrong spot.
鲸鱼走向了错误的地点
It could have been aggression. Who knows?
这可能是一种侵犯 但又有谁知道呢?
But it was not the trainer's fault at all, watching that video.
但这绝对不是训练者的失误 在我看了那盘录像之后
When I saw the video of the killer whale landing on John,
当我看到虎鲸猛烈撞击约翰的时候
I mean, it just absolutely took my breath away.
我是说 我感觉停止了呼吸
I gasped.
我倒吸一口气
I watched it two or three times,
我看了两三次
and every time I saw that, I just gasped.
每次我看到那个场景的时候 我都倒吸一口气
I could not believe what I was seeing.
我简直不敢相信我所看到的
What kept his body together is--
保证他身体在一起的是--
his wetsuit basically held him together.
他的潜水服就这么包着他
But I know he's had multiple surgeries
我知道他刚经历过多次手术
and he's got tons of hardware in his body.
他的身体上绑着许多装备
And it's hard for me to believe that I didn't actually see that video
我也很难以置信 我都没有看过这个视频
while I was actually an animal trainer
在我还是动物训练员的时候
because it seems to me that every person
因为在我看来 每一个
who works with killer whales should have to watch that video.
和虎鲸共事的人 都该看过这个视频
Tamarie--
泰姆瑞--
you know, Tamarie made mistakes.
你知道 泰姆瑞犯了些错误
The most important one was interacting with whales
最重要的一个错误是 她和鲸鱼们互动
without a spotter.
在没有监视人的情况下
So she's putting her foot on Orkid,
她把她的脚放在欧吉上
she's taking her foot off.
然后再把脚拿开
She's putting her foot on Orkid, her rostrum, she's taking it off.
她把脚靠近欧吉靠近她的嘴 然后拿开
Watching the video, knowing Orkid,
看着这个视频 了解欧吉
your stomach drops because you know what's probably going to happen.
你开始担心因为你不知道将会发生什么
She grabbed her foot.
她抓住了她的脚
Tamarie whips around and she grabs the gate.
泰姆瑞围绕着她 她抓住了出入口
You see her just ripped from the gate.
你看到她被扯离出入口
At this point, Tamarie knows that she's in trouble.
此时此刻 泰姆瑞知道她有麻烦了
She's under the water.
她在水下
Splash and Orkid both have her.
斯普拉什和欧吉都盯上了她
She's totally out of view.
她根本不在我们的视线范围之内
No other trainer knows that this is happening.
其他的训练者都不知道发生了这一切
People start to scream.
人们开始尖叫
It was a park guest that was filming it.
有一个公园游客拍下了这一切
You hear-- you don't see her,
你听到她的声音-- 但你看不到她
but you hear Tamarie surface.
但你能听到泰姆瑞浮出水面
You hear her just scream out, "Somebody help me."
你听到她尖叫 "救命"
And the way she screamed it,
她尖叫的那种方式
it was just such a bloodcurdling--
是那种令人毛骨悚然的
like she knew she was going to die.
就像是她知道她将要死掉一样
Robin-- when he ran over, he made a brilliant decision.
Robin-- 在他跑过去的时候 做了一个明智的决定
He told a trainer to run and take the chain off Kasatka's gate.
他告诉训练者跑开然后解开卡萨特卡的池门的链条
By taking that chain off, it would give the precursor to Orkid
解开链条 相当于给了欧吉一个先导
that Kasatka was coming in.
卡萨特卡游进来
Kasatka's more dominant than Orkid,
它处于支配地位
so Orkid let her go.
所以欧吉放开了她
Her arm, it was U-shaped.
她的胳膊成U型
It was compound fractured.
是复合型骨折
She's very lucky to be alive, that's for sure.
确定的是 她足够幸运能够活着
I believe it's 70 plus, maybe even more,
大概有70起 甚至更多
just killer whale trainer accidents.
误杀鲸鱼驯养员的意外
Maybe 30 of them happened prior to me being actually hired at SeaWorld.
大概有三十起事件发生在我受聘于海底世界之前
And I knew about none of them.
但我一无所知
I've seen animals come out at trainers.
我曾经看过动物袭击驯兽师
Something's wrong.
出问题了
I've seen people get slammed.
我看过驯兽师被猛烈撞击
The whales, they're just playing or-- or they're upset for a second.
那个时刻 鲸鱼或许只是在嬉戏 又或许厌烦了
It was just something that happened, you know?
只是某些问题发生了
This culture of "You get back on the horse
"骑在黑鲸的背上
and you dive back in the water.
在水里潜水是传统项目
And if you're hurt, well, then we've got other people that will replace you."
如果你受伤了 我们会让其他人代替你"
And, "You came a long way. Are you sure you want that?"
"你已经为此付出了很多 这就是你想要的结果吗?"
A SeaWorld trainer is recovering today.
海底世界的驯兽师正重新进行培训
2006年11月29日
after a terrifying ordeal in front of a horrified audience.
当惊魂一幕在观众面前上演之后
幼鲸馆晚间最后一场表演
肯·皮特斯正和体重达5000磅(大致两吨左右)卡拉萨卡准备"一飞冲天"特技
就在潜水后的几秒内 卡拉萨卡咬住了肯的脚
For some reason, the whale just took a different approach
由于某种原因 鲸鱼采取了另外一种方式
to what it was going to do
与之相对
with a very senior, very experienced trainer, Ken Peters,
和一名资历深厚经验丰富的驯兽师 肯·皮特斯
and dragged him to the bottom of the pool
它把他拖入水下
and held him at the bottom.
让他一直在水下呆着
Let him go, picked him up,
放开他 又咬住他
took him down again.
再把他拖下水
And these periods he was taken down were pretty close to the mark.
如此循环往复 他已经濒临极限
You know, a minute, a minute 20.
大概有二十分钟
When he was at the surface, he didn't panic,
当他浮出水面 他没有惊慌失措
he didn't thrash, he didn't scream.
没有猛烈挣扎 也没有惊声尖叫
Maybe he's just built that way.
可能他已经那么做过了
But he stroked the whale.
相反地 他只是轻轻拍打鲸鱼
And the whale let go of one foot and grabbed the other.
鲸鱼放开他的一只脚 又咬住另一只
That's a pretty deep pool and he took him right down.
水池很深 它又把驯兽师拖下水
I think that's to two atmospheres of pressure.
我认为这是两个大气压的压力
Apparently, Mr. Peters is an experienced scuba diver
显然 皮特斯先生很擅长潜水
and I think that knowledge probably contributed
相关知识让他知道
to how he was able to be hauled down there
如何不被拖倒
that quickly and stay calm and know what to do.
以致沉着冷静 想出对策
He knew what he was doing because you can see him actually in the film.
他很清楚自己在做什么 这点真实显现在纪录片里
It's-- the def is so good, you can see him ventilating.
他很了不起 你能看见他在换气
You can see him ventilating really hard.
大口大口地换气
So he knows about swimming and diving and being underwater.
他熟识如何水下游泳
He may have been assuming he was going under again.
他甚至想到还会被拖下去
I did not walk away unimpressed by his calm demeanor
我被他镇定的举止震撼到了
during that whole affair.
在整个过程中
I would be scared shitless.
我肯定会被吓得屁滚尿流
He was near to the end.
他体力不支了
Presumably, Ken Peters had a relationship with this whale.
大概 肯·皮特斯和鲸鱼有着良好的关系
Maybe he did. Maybe that's what saved him.
或许他这么做了才能得以逃脱
But Peters got the whale to let him go.
最终皮特斯还是让鲸鱼放开了他
And they strung a net across.
他们拉开渔网
And Ken Peters pulled himself over the float line
肯·皮特斯迅速翻过浮绳
and swam like a demon to a slide-out
奋力向岸边游去
because the whale was coming right behind him.
因为鲸鱼正尾随其后
The whale jumped over and came right after him.
它越过了浮绳 径直向他游来
He tried to stand up and run.
他站起来跑开
Of course, his feet were damaged.
他的脚受伤了
I mean, he just fell and he scrambled.
他竭力跑开 摔倒了
And they take this as a prime example
他们把他当做典范
of their training working.
在他们的培训工作中
And they say, "Just stand back and stay calm," and that did work.
"沉着冷静 就有生机"
They claim this as a victory
他们把这宣称为工作中的
of how they do business.
一场胜利
And maybe so, but it can also be interpreted
或许如此 不过也很容易解释
as a hair's breadth away from another fatality.
千钧一发 命悬一线
Hi, Shamu. Hi, everybody.
哈喽 虎鲸 大家好
We're the Johnsons from Detroit, Michigan.
我们是来自底特律 密歇根州的约翰逊一家
We sure had a great time when we visited SeaWorld.
参观海洋世界很愉快
It's one of our favorite places.
那是我们最喜欢去的地方之一
Yeah, I like the part when Shamu gets everybody wet.
是的 我喜欢虎鲸喷水把大家都弄湿
When the whales get close to the glass
鲸鱼靠近玻璃
and start kicking out the water?
开始拍打池水
Whamo! You're a goner.
你已经是落汤鸡了
Orange County's sheriff's deputies have identified the 27-year-old man
奥兰治的警长助理证实一名27岁男子的尸体
found dead in a killer whale's tank at SeaWorld.
被发现在海洋世界虎鲸的游泳池里
The victim is Daniel P. Dukes from South Carolina.
受害人是来自南卡罗来纳州的丹尼尔·P·杜克斯
Dukes was found yesterday draped over the back of Tilikum,
杜克斯昨天被发现在提里库姆的背上
1999年7月7日
the largest orca held in captivity.
那是在圈养中的最大虎鲸
Well, all I know is the public relations version of it--
我了解大众对此怎么看
he was a young man that had been arrested
他坐过牢
not long before he snuck into SeaWorld.
在偷溜进海洋世界前没多久
Maybe he climbed the barbed wire fence
或许他爬上周边带刺的铁丝围栏
around the perimeter and stayed after hours.
呆了很久
Perfect story line-- a mentally disturbed guy
完美的故事链-一个精神失常的家伙
hides in the park after hours and strips his clothes off
匿藏公园数小时 脱掉衣服
and decides he wants to have a magical experience with an orca
想要和虎鲸有次不同寻常的经历
and drowns because he became hypothermic.
体温过低导致溺水
Right. So that's the story line
这就是故事链
and none of us were there to know the difference.
毫无疑点
He was not detected by the night watch trainers
他没有被夜间巡视员发现
who were presumably at that station.
本应在那个位置的
There are cameras all over SeaWorld.
海洋世界到处都有监控
There are cameras all over the back of Shamu Stadium
虎鲸游泳池后面那里也有
pointing every which way.
摄向四面八方
There are underwater cameras.
还有水下摄像机
I find it hard to believe that nobody knew until the morning
很难相信直到早晨大家才发现
that there was a body in there.
有一具尸体在那里
They have a night watch trainer every night.
每晚都有夜间巡视员
That person didn't hear any splashing or screaming?
难道那个人没有听到任何水花四溅 有人呼救的声音吗
I mean, I just find that really suspicious.
这很可疑
One of the employees--
雇员里
I don't know if it was a physical therapist or somebody--
我不清楚是否有理疗师或者有人
was coming in in the morning and there was Tilikum,
在早晨进来发现在提里库姆
you know, with a dead guy, a dead, naked guy on his back,
的背上有一具赤裸的尸体
kind of parading him around the back pool.
载着他在水里游
The public relations spin on this was that
大众对这件事加以渲染
he was kind of a drifter and died of hypothermia.
他是流浪汉 死于体温过低
But the medical examiner reports
但是法医的报告
were more graphic than that.
更加真实
For example, Tilikum stripped him,
例如 提里库姆咬住了他
bit off his genitals.
咬掉了他的生殖器
There was bite marks all over his body.
全身都是咬痕
Now, whether that was post-death or pre-death, I don't know.
我不清楚哪种说法更加确切
But, yeah, all I can comment on
但我能确信的是
is that the guy definitely jumped in the wrong pool.
那个家伙跳错了水池
So why keep Tilikum there?
所以为什么要把提里库姆养在那里?
This guy, he has a proven track record of killing people.
那个家伙有杀过人的记录
He's clearly a liability to the institution.
它显然有法律责任
Why keep him around? Well, it's quite simple to answer.
为什么让它在那里 不难回答
And that is that his semen is worth a lot of money.
它的精液很值钱
Over the years, Tilikum has been
多年以来 提里库姆已经是
one of the main breeding whales at SeaWorld.
海洋世界主要饲养鲸
It's brilliant because they can inseminate way more female whales,
因为他们对它和更多的雌鲸鱼进行人工受精
because they can just get his sperm and freeze it.
他们能提取它的精子并冻结
And then he's basically operating as a sperm bank.
它的主要功能就是作为精子库
In a reputable breeding program, rule number one
在一个良好的育种规则里 第一诫就是
is you certainly would not breed an animal that has shown
你要确定饲养的动物没有
a history of aggression towards humans.
攻击过人的历史
Imagine if you had a pit bull who had killed.
假设你有一头杀死人的公牛
That animal would have likely been put down.
很有可能就会被储藏起来
But in the entire SeaWorld collection--
但是在整个海洋世界的饲养中
it's like 54% of the whales in SeaWorld's collection
大概54%的鲸鱼
now have Tilikum's genes.
都有提里库姆的因子
The fall is to assume that all killer whales are like Tilikum.
假设所有的虎鲸都像提里库姆
You have to look at their learning history from birth.
你必须从它们出生时就开始观察
You have to understand why Tilikum was a hazard
你必须明白为什么提里库姆是个危险
to anybody in the water.
对于在水里的任何人
And you have to understand that none of the other killer whales at SeaWorld
你也要理解海洋世界的其他虎鲸
that are in that system are that way.
如出一辙
What about the incident at Loro Parque?
关于发生在loro parque的意外呢
*loro parque:西班牙加那利群岛特纳利夫岛的一个动物园
First of all, I-- I can't--
首先  我不能
I can't speak with specificity about Loro Parque.
很精确地评述
I wasn't there.
我不在那里
In fact, I know very little about it.
实际上 我了解甚少
Probably about as much as the general public knows.
或许和大众了解的一样多
加那利群岛 西班牙
他告诉我有一些重要的事要跟我说
他跪下然后向我求婚了
埃斯特法尼娅·罗德里格斯
非常浪漫
当然我说"我愿意"
他问"真的吗?"
我说"当然"
他从来就没期望能去训练鲸鱼
他想当一名录音师
他一直都很喜欢动物也尝试与它们相处
他也喜欢这份工作 也试着去做 为这份工作倾尽全力
Loro Parque, it's in the Canary Islands,
Loro Parque在加那利群岛
which is an autonomous region of Spain.
是西班牙的一个自治区
It's the largest tourist attraction in all of Spain.
也是一个著名的旅游胜地
And when SeaWorld sent the orcas to Loro Parque,
当海洋世界把虎鲸送到Loro Parque
everybody was always questioning,
所有人都在质疑
苏珊娜·阿里
Loro Parque动物园前监控视频总监
like, how did they make that leap to send four young orcas
他们是如何把四条幼虎鲸
to a park off the west coast of Africa
送到非洲西海岸的一个公园
with trainers who-- a lot of them had never been around orcas before?
让一些毫无经验的驯兽师来训练它们?
Nothing was ready.
一切都那么措手不及
The venue wasn't ready.
地点同样亟需商讨
It wasn't ready for the orcas, it wasn't ready for a show.
一切一切都没做好准备
The owner of the park didn't want to lose revenue
公园的所有者不想花费收益
by shutting down the pools and repairing them.
在关掉水池重新整修上面
So for three years, the animals ate the pools
三年来 鲸鱼们一直在啃咬水池
and for three years the animals had problems--
直到问题出现
with their teeth, with their stomachs.
他们的牙齿 他们的胃
So that's the reason why these animals
这就是为什么鲸鱼们
are enduring the endoscope procedures.
要接受内镜检查
Back up. Now back up, back up.
后退 现在后退 后退
Those are still SeaWorld's animals
那些仍然是海洋世界的鲸鱼们
and they are responsible for those animals.
他们为之负责的鲸鱼们
Loro Parque doesn't have a good reputation.
Loro Parque名声不是很好
People that work in the business know the reputation of places
驯兽师们知道关于这个地方的名声
and Loro Parque does not have a good reputation.
而Loro Parque的名声也确实不怎么样
They didn't spend the same amount of time as the SeaWorld trainers,
他们不像海洋世界的驯兽师花费大量的时间
did not go through the same regimen
运用相同的训练
that the SeaWorld trainers went through.
像海洋世界驯兽师那样
You know, and Alexis really was the best trainer.
亚历克西斯已经是最好的驯兽师了
And I did say-- I said, "You're the only trainer there
我说过"你是这里唯一的"
that can hold his own with a SeaWorld trainer."
能和海洋世界驯兽师相媲美
And I said, "But you need to be careful."
我还说"但是你还是要多加注意"
Anywhere along the line it could have been stopped
这一切本可能被停止
because everyone knew it was a tragedy waiting to happen.
因为人人知道悲剧很有可能会发生
But no one ever did anything about it.
但没人为此付诸行动
And in the end,
最终
it was the best trainer who lost his life.
最好的驯兽师失去了他的生命
亚历克西斯死前在海洋世界受训了12个月
Those were SeaWorld's whales.
那些是海洋世界的鲸鱼
They were trained using SeaWorld's techniques.
它们曾经用海洋世界的方法来训练
And their training was being supervised at the time of the fatal accident
致命意外发生时它们的训练正被监督着
by one of their senior trainers from San Diego.
是来自圣地亚哥一名经验丰富的驯兽师
海洋世界律师
你提到了...Loro Pargue
那是海洋世界拥有的动物园吗?
海洋世界驯兽师主管
凯莉·克拉克
不 并不是
那里的驯兽师获取了你们在海洋世界的经验吗?
没有
For somebody to get up and say in a court of law
在法庭上人人起立并陈述观点
they have no knowledge of the linkages
他们对海洋世界和在特纳利夫岛的公园的
between SeaWorld and this park in Tenerife is well--
联系一无所知
either she doesn't know and is telling the truth
她甚至不知道她是在讲述事实
or it's just a bold-faced lie.
还是一个厚颜无耻的谎话
As trainers, we never forget Shamu's true potential.
作为驯兽师 我们永远不会忘记虎鲸的真正潜力
We see it each and every day.
我们每时每刻都能看到
That's why all of our interactions are very carefully thought out,
这就是为什么我们所有的互动都异常小心
especially our water work interaction.
尤其是水中作业
Whoa!
哇
You big dork.
你这个笨蛋
Especially our water work interactions
特别是水中作业
because they're potentially the most dangerous.
因为它们存在着潜在的威胁
I'd been expecting it since the second person was killed.
我一直在等着第二个人的死亡
I'd been expecting somebody to be killed by Tilikum.
我一直在等着有人被提里库姆杀死
I'm surprised it took as long as it did.
这一切都变成了现实
First tonight, a six-ton killer whale
第一晚 一个六吨的虎鲸
has lived up to its name, killing an experienced trainer
无愧于自己的名字杀死了一名有经验的驯兽师
at SeaWorld, Orlando, today.
今天 在奥兰多的海洋世界
A tourist at an earlier show
一位游客在早先的表演中
said the animal seemed agitated.
反映鲸鱼好像很焦躁
Trainers complained the whales weren't cooperating.
驯兽师抱怨鲸鱼不肯合作
The whole show, the main show,
压轴的鲸鱼表演
was a disaster that day.
是那天的一场灾难
There was, you know, whales chasing each other
鲸鱼互相追逐
and eventually the trainers decided that they had to stop the show
最终驯兽师们不得不取消表演
because they couldn't get the whales under control.
因为鲸鱼失控难以控制
Tilikum was in the back pool
提里库姆在后面的水池
set up to do a Dine with Shamu performance with Dawn.
准备和道恩一起做表演
Likely she saw what had gone on during the main show
很有可能她知道主秀发生了什么
and so she had probably felt more pressure to do a good show.
所以她倍感压力
Yay!
耶
When you watch the whole video, you can see
当你看全部录像 你会发现
that Tilikum is actually really with Dawn
提里库姆一直和道恩在一起
in the beginning of the video.
在录像的开始
There's a couple of behaviors that she asks him to do
这是她要求它做的伙伴的表现
where Tilikum justjumps right in
提里库姆跳在哪里
and he does exactly what she asks him to do.
它的确按要求做了
There seemed to be a point in the session
这是任务中的关键之处
where things went south, so to speak.
慢慢的事情朝相反的方向发展了 所以说呢
And in my humble opinion,
以我鄙见
it was at that missed bridge-- whistle bridge,
这里缺了一个信号-口哨的信号
on the perimeter pec wave.
在洲际派克波之前
*洲际派克波:暂译名 为一种特技表演
She asked him to do a perimeter pec wave
她让他做洲际派克波
where she asked him to basically go all the way around the pool
她要求它饶水池游一圈
and wave his pectoral flipper.
挥舞它的胸鳍鳍
And she blows her whistle...
她吹了个口哨
- There we go. - ...which is a bridge,
-这就好   -这就是信号
which tells the animal that, okay, you've done a good job.
告诉鲸鱼你做得好的信号
Come back and get food.
回来进食
But he missed that cue.
但是他错过了那个暗示
He likes waving so much. That's beyond waving.
它太喜欢挥舞了 以至于过量了
And he went all the way around the pool
它一直在绕水池
on this perimeter pec wave.
在这个派克波里
That's all right. We're going to let him keep on waving.
非常好 让它一直保持下去吧
My interpretation is that he didn't hear the whistle.
我的理解是它没有听到那个口哨
So not only did he not hear the bridge,
所以没有听到那个信号
then he went and did a perfect behavior and came back,
然后它继续 完成一个完美的动作 就游回来了
and what he got was what we call a three-second neutral response,
它得到了一个我们称之为三秒钟中性反应的信号
which is just a way to let the animal know,
是一种让鲸鱼知道
"No, you didn't do the correct thing.
"你做错了的信号
You're not going to get rewarded. And then we're going to move on."
你不会得到奖励 我们继续"
And then you can also see through the video
然后你从录像中可以看到
that Dawn is running out of food.
道恩用完了食物
The animals can sense
鲸鱼能感受到
when you're getting to the bottom of your bucket of fish,
当篮子里的鱼见底了
because they can hear the ice clanging around
因为它们能听见冰发出的叮当声
and the kind of fishy, soupy water at the bottom.
鱼在底部蠕动挣扎的声音
And the handfuls of fish that they're getting delivered by the trainer
它们从驯养员手中得来的鱼
are all getting smaller.
越来越小
So they know that they're coming down to the end of session.
所以它们知道任务结束了
When you see the difference between the beginning of the video
当你从录像中
and the end of the video, you can see
看开头和结尾的不同 你会发现
that he's just not quite on his game anymore.
它完全不在意任务了
There was no food left.
没有食物了
She kept asking him for more and more behaviors.
她让它做越来越多的表演
He wasn't getting reinforced for the behaviors
它的行为没有收到相应的回报
that he was doing correctly.
但它完成得很正确
He probably was frustrated towards the end.
或许最终它沮丧了
Then she walked around the perimeter of G pool.
然后她走到G水池
He followed her.
它跟着她
And then continued over into the rocky ledge area
一直到岩石架区
where she laid down with him to do a relationship session,
她躺在那里要和它一起做合作任务
which is-- it's quiet time, basically.
基本上 它很安静
Tilikum at some point grabbed ahold of her left forearm
提里库姆在某种程度上咬住她的左前臂
and started to drag her and eventually did a barrel roll
开始拖她 最终做了一个翻滚
and pulled her in.
把她拖下去了
It may have started as play or frustration
开始可能是玩乐或者是因为沮丧
and clearly escalated to be very violent behavior
后来显然升级成暴力行为
that I think was anything but play.
我认为这绝不是玩乐
In the end, he basically
最终 它
just completely mutilated that poor girl.
把那个可怜的女孩咬得残缺不全
They were gathering all of the trainers at the Texas park.
德克萨斯州公园聚集了所有的驯兽师
He said, "There's been an accident
他说"发生了一起事故
at the Florida park and a trainer was killed."
在弗罗里达公园 一名驯兽师被杀"
Hearing that it was Dawn, I was-- I couldn't believe it.
听到是道恩 我难以置信
I just remember saying to myself, "Not Dawn.
我清楚记得我对自己说"不是道恩
It can't be Dawn."
不可能是道恩"
He said that-- "And he still has her."
他说"它吃了她"
And I just...
我...
was so disturbed by that
我被搅得心烦意乱
and the reality of how powerless we are.
也意识我们的无能无力
Avulsion, laceration, abrasion, fractures.
撕裂 撕裂伤 磨损 断裂
Fractures and associated hemorrhages.
骨折和相关的出血
Blunt force traumas
钝力外伤
to the main body, to the extremities.
身体上 四肢上
To see this meted out against a trainer...
看着受过训练的驯兽师
and I cannot fathom the reason.
我无法理解原因
It's shocking.
太令人震惊了
The lawyer for OSHA asked me what I thought we'd learned,
OSHA问我或许我们能学到什么
and I'm sitting in the courtroom
我坐在法庭上
and I've got the Keltie Byrne case file in one hand
一手拿着凯尔蒂·拜恩的案例
and I've got Dawn Brancheau in the other.
另一只拿着道恩·布兰切的案例
And they're almost, to the day, 20 years apart.
为了这一天 差不多相隔了二十年
And I'm looking at these two things.
我看着这两件案例
My only answer is, "Nothing."
我唯一的回答就是"没有"
In fact, it's not a damn thing.
事实上 这不是一件该死的事情
We have not learned a damn thing
我们没有学好一件该死的事情
for something like that to happen 20 years apart.
对于类似的事件相隔二十年再次发生
Could you tell if it was an accident or if this--
你可以说这是一场意外或者是
Did this female trainer work with this whale on a regular basis?
这位女驯兽师是否按照正常准则和鲸鱼互动呢
I don't know. What apparently happened is we had a female trainer
我不知道 我只知道我们有一名女驯兽师
back in the whale holding area.
丧生在鲸鱼池底
She apparently slipped or fell into the tank
她显然不慎滑落水池
and was fatally injured by one of the whales.
被其中一只鲸鱼造成致命伤害
At first, SeaWorld reported that a trainer slipped
起初 海洋世界只是报告一名驯兽师
and fell in the water and was drowned.
不慎滑落水池 溺水而亡
So that was the first report.
这是第一篇报道
It wasn't until eyewitness accounts disputed that
知道目击者们出现带来争议
that they had to go back in their huddle
他们不得不重新计划
and say, "Wait a minute. We gotta come up with a new plan."
说道 稍等片刻"我们想出了一个新说法"
New tonight-- SeaWorld has confirmed
今晚-海洋世界证实
the killer whale pulled the woman into the water.
是虎鲸把那个女驯兽师拖下水的
She didn't fall into the tank
她没有落入水池
as the sheriff's department initially reported.
就像警察部门最初报道那样
The new plan is that he grabbed her ponytail.
新说法是它咬住她的马尾辫
This is a subtle way of placing the blame on Dawn's shoulders.
这是一个很微妙的说法把责任归咎到道恩身上
She shouldn't have had a long ponytail,
她没有那么长的马尾辫
or if she did have that ponytail, it should have been up in a bun.
如果她有那么长的马尾辫 也是应该被盘起来的
Dawn, if she was standing here with me right now,
道恩 如果她和我现在在一起
would tell you that it was her mistake
会告诉你这是她的错
in allowing that to happen.
允许这种情况发生
They blamed her.
他们指责她
How dare you?
你们算什么?
How disrespectful for you to blame her
如此无礼地指责她
when she's not even alive to defend herself.
当她不能活着为自己辩护
He grabbed her ponytail and pulled her into the water.
它咬住她的马尾辫把她拖入水中
That's as simple as it gets.
这很简单
There are photographs of plenty of other trainers
有很多其他驯兽师的照片
doing exactly the same thing that she was doing,
和她做着同样的事情
so I knew that SeaWorld was lying about the fact that this was her fault.
所以我知道海洋世界撒谎了说这是她的错
The ponytail, in all likelihood, is just a tale.
马尾辫 在所有的可能里 只是一个故事
The safety spotter, who apparently didn't actually see the takedown,
安全监视人员显示没看到这一幕
came up with that.
扔继续下去
- Are you excited? - Yeah!
-你们高兴吗   -是的
During the spotter's testimony,
在安全监视人员的证词里
OSHA pushed him to say that he wasn't really sure
OSHA让他说他不确定
that it was her ponytail that was in the whale's mouth,
是她的马尾辫在鲸鱼的嘴里
that he just saw her underwater and he assumed it was the ponytail.
他只是看到她在水下 他猜测那是马尾辫
OSHA contends that the whale came up
OSHA认为鲸鱼浮出水面
and grabbed Dawn Brancheau's arm,
咬住道恩·布兰切的胳膊
saying that that was another level of aggressiveness.
认为这是某种程度的攻击
And again, SeaWorld is saying it was not an aggressive move.
然后海洋世界说这不是攻击行为
One of SeaWorld's top curators, Chuck Tompkins,
海洋世界的馆长之一查克·汤普金
said when Dawn Brancheau was pulled off that ledge,
当道恩·布兰切被拉下平台
it wasn't necessarily aggressive behavior by the whale.
并不是鲸鱼的有意攻击行为
The initial grab was not an act of aggression.
起初的抓咬并不是攻击行为
This is not a crazed animal.
这不是一个疯狂的动物
The industry has a vested interest in spinning these
这个行业有利可图
so that the animals continue to appear
所以这些鲸鱼能继续出现
like cuddly teddy bears that are completely safe.
就像可爱的泰迪熊 这是完全安全的
You know, that sells a lot of Shamu dolls,
已经卖了很多虎鲸的玩具
it sells a lot of tickets at the gate, and that's the story line
还有很多演出的门票 这就是故事链
that they're going to continue to stick with for as long as they can.
他们会竭尽所能继续坚持
Recognize that those that say this is a crazed animal
认识到这些鲸鱼是疯狂的动物
that acted out and grabbed Dawn maliciously,
恶意地咬住道恩
they want to prove the theorem that captivity makes animals crazy.
他们想证明是圈养把它们逼疯了
And that is just false.
这是错误的
All whales in captivity have a bad life.
所有圈养的鲸鱼生活都不好
They're all emotionally destroyed.
它们被情绪化所摧毁
They're all psychologically traumatized,
他们在心理上受到创伤
so they are ticking time bombs.
所以它们都是定时炸弹
It's not just Tilikum.
不只是提里库姆
We have to separate what happened to Dawn--
我们对发生在道恩身上的事情很遗憾
and, as tragic as it is, no one wants to ever see it happen again.
这样的悲剧没有人想再看到了
Can SeaWorld create an environment
海洋世界能创造一个环境
where it never happens again?
让其不再发生吗
Yes, I absolutely believe they can.
我相信他们能够做到
What if there were no SeaWorlds?
如果没有了海洋世界呢
I can't imagine a society, with the value we put
我不能想象一个社会 有着有价值的哺乳动物
on marine mammals, if those parks didn't exist.
如果这些公园不在存在
I'm not at all interested in having my daughter,
我不能让我的女儿对此感兴趣
who is three and a half,
三岁半
grow up thinking that it's normalized
认为这是正常的在成长过程中
to have these intelligent, highly evolved animals
这些聪明高度进化的动物
in concrete pools.
在有限的水池里
I don't want her to think that's how we treat the kin
我不希望她认为我们是那样对待在这个星球上的
that we find ourselves around on this planet.
我们周边的同类(都是哺乳动物)
I think it's atrocious.
我认为这是糟糕透顶的
This hearing is expected to last all week
这场听证会预计将持续一周
with OSHA continuing to work toward this theory--
随着OSHA继续推行这个说法
that SeaWorld knew there was a calculated risk of injury or death,
海洋世界知道有一定的理论
but put trainers in the water with the whales anyway,
但还是任意让驯兽师在水中与鲸鱼互动
while SeaWorld will say that Dawn Brancheau's death
虽然海洋世界会说道恩·布兰切的死
was an isolated incident.
只是一个偶然事件
Reporting live in Seminole County, Dave McDaniel, WESH 2 News.
WESH2新闻台的戴夫·迈克丹尼尔在塞米诺尔郡为您报道
There's something wrong.
哪里出问题了
You know with Tilikum that there's something wrong and that's--
你知道提里库姆出了问题
when you have a relationship with that animal and you--
但当你和某个鲸鱼有了关系
you understand that he's killing not to be a savage.
你会明白它的杀戮不是野蛮残暴的
He's not killing because he's just crazy.
它不是因为疯了才杀戮
He's not killing because he doesn't know what he's doing.
它不是因为不知道自己在做什么才杀戮
He's killing because he's frustrated
它杀戮是因为它很沮丧
and he's got aggravations and he doesn't know how to--
它恼怒是因为它不知所措
he has no outlet for it.
它找不到出口
Now Tilikum is spending a great deal of time by himself
提里库姆现在大部分时间都是独自一人
and basically floating lifeless in a pool.
漫无目地在水池里漂浮着
Three hours now...
三个小时过去了
and he hasn't moved.
它还没有动
They try to sugarcoat it by saying,
他们尝试用糖衣炮弹
"He comes out in the front pool every once in a while.
"它每隔一会就会浮出水面
Now he's doing shows."
现在它在做表演"
Really? You know what he does in a show?
你知道它在表演里做什么吗
He does a few bows
不断鞠躬
and then he goes back in his little jail cell.
然后回到自己的小牢房里
That's his life.
这就是它的生活
I feel sad for Tilikum.
我为提里库姆感到悲哀
A regal thing like him swimming around the tank
在水池里游来游去
with his fin flopped over like that
来回翻转
compared to a wild bull killer whale that size,
与野生的虎鲸相比较
which is one of the most kinetic and dynamic things
这是最有活力的事情之一
you can imagine...
你能想象到
I feel sad when I see him.
每当我看见它我都感到很悲哀
It's time to stop the shows.
是时候结束表演了
It's time to stop forcing animals to perform
是时候停止强迫动物去表演了
in basically a circus environment.
在类似于马戏团的环境里
And they should release the animals that are young enough
他们应该把放生那些年轻健康的黑鲸们
and healthy enough to be released, and the animals like Tilikum
就像提里库姆一样
who are old and sick and have put in 25 years in the industry
老弱病残已经呆了25年的鲸鱼们
should be released to an open ocean pen
也应该被放生大海
so they can live out their lives
它们才能独立生存
and just experience the natural rhythms of the ocean.
体验海洋的自然规律
This is a multibillion-dollar corporation
这是一个价值数十亿美元的公司
that makes its money through the exploitation of orcas.
通过压榨虎鲸来获取利益
They're not suitable to have in captivity.
它们根本不适合圈养
The whales are really bored.
鲸鱼们已经厌烦了
You deprive them of all this environmental stimulation.
人们已经剥夺了它们对环境的刺激
I think that in 50 years,
我想在五十年内
we'll look back and go, "My God, what a barbaric time."
我们会反思"天啊那是多么野蛮的时代"
Dawn Brancheau-- DB, dream big.
道恩·布兰切-DB 远大梦想
Dawn was the most loving, giving person you ever met.
道恩是你见过最可爱最有爱心的人
Her smile just radiated.
她的微笑很有感染力
She's comp-- she fulfilled her life.
她的人生很有成就感
We saw whales
我们看见了那些鲸鱼
swimming in straight lines with straight dorsal fins.
在海里径直地游着
I was so honored to be there.
我很欣慰
And I was so thankful that I had sunglasses on
很庆幸我戴了墨镜
because the tears were kind of coming out.
因为我的泪水早已涌出
And it was moving.
太感人了
谢谢观看!
树屋字幕组
荣誉出品
\\本字幕仅供学习交流,严禁用于商业途径//